[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
developers are you ready it's time to
upgrade your data platform to inner
systems iris
choose your language choose your tools
choose your environment
collaborate build faster and deploy more
efficiently
when you can make faster decisions
there's no telling what you'll create
ready set code start coding for free
visit intersystems.com try to try iris
welcome to software engineering radio
i'm your host gavin henry and today my
guest is brian foy brian foy is one of
the most prophyllic authors in the pearl
programming community
he's the author of mastering pearl and
learning pearl 6 and the co-author of
learning pearl
intermediate pearl pearl programming
effective program and others
you get the idea he helps people and
companies use pearl through education
training and consulting his latest book
is about preparing for pearl 7.
brian welcome to software engineering
radio is there anything i missed in your
bio that you'd like to add
oh no i think people who interview me
know more about what i've done than than
i can remember i think
you've got most of it there's actually a
lot of stuff online that you probably
aren't aware of but there's lots of good
things to choose from there so
that's great during the show we'll be
talking about pearl's history
use cases successes and what it's like
now with the rest of the show
talking about pearl seven but i'd like
to start with an overview of where pearl
came from
when you would reach for it so what is
pearl and is it like any other
programming language
well geez you really have to go back in
history to to think about this
so the short story is that pearl started
as a sort of a pet project of larry wall
he was
doing some stuff to coordinate a bunch
of machines as a sys admin and
some of the tools he were using wasn't
really cutting it to his satisfaction so
he started cobbling together this other
thing
and he was taking bits from awk and said
and c
and all sorts of other things to make
this tool that
worked for him he released it i
think it was in 1987 on one of the use
nets groups if anyone remembers what
those are
and then from there other people got
involved and they started using it and
they added in henry spencer's regex
engine so and that's where pearl really
made its reputation as
this text processing stuff from there it
went on to pearl three was really
popular and then
when they uh had it popular enough to
make a book out of it they bumped it up
to pearl 4 and that's where that first
learning pearl came from
larry wall and randall schwartz really
kicked this stuff off
and at that point we were going through
the dot-com boom this was you know late
80s early 90s
people were doing all sorts of stuff to
to get their information onto the web
and
pearl was a great way to do that it
didn't require a lot of
learning or experience to do very simple
things and people were
really attracted to that that's one of
its um famous sayings isn't it
about things being simple yeah in fact i
think that's on the cover of one of my
books it's the uh
make the simple things easy and the hard
things possible
it was talking about this idea that if
you do this all the time you shouldn't
have to type that much to do it
and if there are some things that are
really tough they should be tractable
they should be workable you shouldn't
have to spend a whole lot of time
working on something
and for the the casual programmer or the
baby programmer which a lot of people
talked about at that time that was
perfect and if you're looking back on
this now you've got to imagine that this
is before something like php existed
which people often think is one of
pearl's competitors but
it was the it's now the tool that is
sort of filling that gap where
i just want to put this little teeny bit
of text right here
and i don't care about anything else
with programming but you know that
used to be uh really hard to do and it
was really hard to do before
pearl at that time there wasn't many
languages that came with a
pc or a unix distribution was there oh
jeez
the pain i remember having to install
things on a new machine
like today you can just spin up a docker
and put anything you want on it
practically for free almost no
investment in time but back then
if you installed an operating system you
got this very bare thing and
then you had to say okay well let's look
at my notebook and see what i want
okay how am i going to install this how
am i going gonna install this
i remember i would actually buy a cd
from a third-party vendor of all the
stuff i wanted on my solaris machine
it was already pre-packaged and i mean
now you just get that from your
your package manager it just sort of
comes with it
but i don't remember what else i was
using at the time
uh i was a scientist so fortran was a
big thing and
that's still a big thing isn't it that's
um well yeah you don't want to change
the programs because nobody knows how
they work
yeah the kids today don't know how easy
they've got it do they it's just we just
get to harder and harder problems
uh yeah but pearl was revolutionary for
its time and the way it handled things
and the way it
it was more for the masses and for the
people who are going to do this
every day all day so i think you've
touched on the fact that
it can be simple for those that want it
to be simple but it
can stay with you and grow with you
that's the sort of message i'm hearing
yeah it's the more you get into it the
more power you have
but you don't have to get all the way
into it just to get a little bit of
power
not to throw aspersions on any other
sort of language but
one of my friends is learning haskell
right now and that's you have to
do quite a bit of work and and sort of
buy into a whole lot of stuff
to be useful in that language but that's
fine that's the way they're doing things
and that's the way
that thing is set up pearl not so much
here you can read this book in in a day
you can be writing programs that might
be solving some of your
your small problems and then you don't
have to think about it so much we don't
particularly care if you are a full-time
pearl programmer
and it's one of a handful of languages
that come with your
linux distribution or does it come on
mac os
yeah well pearl comes with the mac
as does ruby and python but apple have
has said that they're going to try to
get rid of the scripting languages as
part of the default install which i
think makes sense
for them they've been slimming down
their their core installation and stuff
like that
i don't know how that's going to shake
out for people who just assume that it's
there
it's very easy to install perl as well
as python and ruby
if you want it but you have to know that
you want it
uh people might be running programs and
they don't even know what the languages
is in
so we'll see how that goes but i'm sure
there'll be some way that at least the
pearl community
will respond to that and make that
really easy for those people who
who suddenly find it's not there anymore
does it come with its own interpreter
or compiler or how does that language
actually work
there's pearl so if we just start from
sort of the bare metal
pearl is a is an interpreter and a
compiler all at the same time i don't
want to get too technical with that
basically you write a program in a text
file and we don't particularly care
what editor you use we don't make you
use an ide or any sort of particular
environment
that text file is is given to this thing
we call the interpreter
but what it really does is two things
it's going to go through
your program and and look at it and make
it into some sort of intermediate
representation
and that's the point we're going to find
out about all your syntax errors and
other
sort of wacky things and then once it's
done that and it's had a complete look
at everything that you're going to do
that same program is going to then run
whatever you've told it to do so this is
all sort of happening
in one step for people who've been
around they might
be used to something like java where you
compile something and you end up with
some
some stuff and then you hand that stuff
to something else to actually run it or
pass it around and someone can run it
without the compilation step
we don't have that in perl it's the same
thing
that does the interpretation and the
running
which means you need pearl somehow to
actually run the program
there's various ways that people have
come up with to package pearl if
you want to distribute it and you don't
know if they have it or not
but for the most part that one thing we
call the pearl interpreter is handling
both of those jobs and that's generally
parallel with the lowercase p
as the interpreter yeah so so this is a
a funny bit of history there's when we
talk about pearl the language
we mostly use an uppercase p then p
lowercase e lowercase r lowercase l but
it hasn't always been that way
if you look back at the first books on
pearl learning pearl and programming
pearl and these had the pink covers
these were some of the first o'reilly
nutshell books
they both had lowercase pearl
the whole word on it because it wasn't
until later that i think
randall schwartz decided that he was
going to distinguish between the two
there's a language
which we're going to make this proper
noun uppercase p
pearl and then there's an interpreter
which is this the name of the program
that sits there on your computer and
does things and
since most programs have all lower case
names we're just going to call that all
lowercase pearl
which is one of the tougher things to do
when you're writing about pearl
like randall and i have done in many
books and i've
is decide which of those fit
what you're trying to say when you say
pearl are you talking about the language
are you talking about
this specific action of this thing
that's going to run your program
sometimes it's not so clear it it's
actually sort of surprising
thanks um you mentioned power lower case
p e r l is an interpreter
and can be a compiler but doesn't it
have a virtual machine
element now or is that in another part
of the language
where do we sit with that no i there
might be
something like that behind the scenes
but i'm not aware of it
i'm i'm not much of an internals guy so
how they actually get things done
behind that thing that's that's called
pearl i'm not entirely sure it it's not
something like where you have to have a
complete world for it
say like small talk or some of these
other languages that just want to know
everything that's happening
it's it's basically something that you
can run on you know unix windows mac
something like this
just straight on their their stock
operating system
and get your results um i was kind of
meeting the
i think it's the power vm for pearl six
oh
oh were you talking about pearl six now
well i was trying to differentiate
between
ah okay so we're getting into a little
bit later in the show but um so
i can give you the quick answer on that
yeah cool so what we're talking about
now
when we say just purl is everyone's
gonna default to talking about
pearl major version 5. in
around 2000 a group of people decided
that it was time for pearl
to jump to his next major version so we
have gotten
pearl 0 at about 1987 i forget
the year for pearl 4 but pearl 5 was 94
95 something like that and then in 2000
we're talking about
what have we learned in the last five
years what do people want what's the
future look like and they started work
on pearl six
larry wall decided it was going to be
the community's rewrite of pearl
and we're going to basically have
everything available to us if we wanted
to change it
and that's not quite what happened in
history so for various reasons
pearl 6 didn't really replace pearl 5.
it's actually now called
this language raku and it's its own
thing and it stands on its own
and it's it's nice i like it it has some
very very nice features
i have a book called learning pearl six
and we haven't updated the title yet to
learning raku
but that's sort of gone off on its own
and i think that is the
best answer for that particular language
i think standing on its own and and
being able to carve out its own niche in
history
is a good result that's a perfect answer
so it's kind of like um yeah ipv4
and ipv6 they they're related but
they just went off separately everyone's
been trying to replace it
i you know not to sort of interrupt my
answer here and that but i just read
this nice essay about
that there's now a backlash against ipv6
because of just the way
it's being administered but anyway who
would have thought that like 10 years
ago
i think i'll probably do a show on that
by itself because it's a whole
yeah it's a whole thing it's really cool
so let
let's go back to pearl 6 for a minute so
in 2000 we have this chance to do
anything we want we don't have to
preserve backwards compatibility we
don't have to do things in the same way
and one of the main factors was that as
pearl had developed and all is coded
sort of accreted in
the thing that makes the interpreter is
that developers are having a tougher and
tougher time
maintaining it just like you know sort
of any software project that lives
for decades there's going to be code
eventually that you want to get rid of
or behavior you want to get rid of
anyway
one of the things that they have this
idea for is this virtual machine called
parrot
now it started off as a joke and i think
simon cousins might have been the person
who started it
was why don't you know i think it came
from monty python
you know the dead parrot sketch or
something like that but
why don't we have a multi-language
interpreter
or virtual machine that we can write all
this stuff to and now
this new version of pearl which would
have been pearl 6 can target this
vm and tickle can
target this vm and java can target this
vm and ruby and so on
but not only that if perl can come in
and write byte codes for this vm
this vm can decompile it and go back out
to anything it understands
one of these things was called parrot
and that's not quite what happened
it went on for a while and finally died
or i guess it's
not dead yet or it's just resting or
whatever it is
well it's it's important to lay that
foundation of information down for
yeah to lead us on to pearl seven so
thanks for that explanation
just i'll add one more thing here pearl
six the raku
thing which is not pearl 5 raku
is on a different vm called more which
is meta object
something on a runtime so we got the
same idea
but it's not in pearl 5 yet so a couple
of important questions
for new folks to pearl where is it used
and how popular is it
just a briefly oh geez that would it'd
be wonderful to know the answers to
those things
or maybe where isn't it used so why
where isn't it used is easier so
so i used to work as a as a radiation
worker in a national lab
uh i had a career in physics before i
got into the programming
and there are all these disclaimers
whenever you would write software that
is not going to be used for
medical equipment aircraft control or
nuclear power plants
so i'm pretty sure pearl's not
controlling any of those things
but where it is used i mean i've seen it
used in every sort of sector government
academia industry
uh science it's a great way to transform
data and
almost everywhere needs to transform
data it's not as popular as it used to
be and that's
no secret i mean i've been with pearl
since the early 90s
when everyone wanted to be a parole
programmer
and you could make a bunch of money if
you had a pulse
and you said you knew pearl even if you
didn't know pearl
from then we have a lot more choices now
and that's when people talk about this
they forget that
the decline in popularity of something
also has to look at
how people are choosing to solve their
problems and we have a lot more choices
now
so of course you're not going to be king
of the hill
when there's so many other places people
can go
php solved the problem that a lot of
people had and they're using pearl for
so more power to them python has shown
up
and they have a sort of a different
focus in their community where
they're very focused on the the science
side
where the libraries and and the things
that people want python is paying
attention to
yeah they're really heavy in machine
learning aren't they yeah most of the
books the moment are about
hold on and and pearl's still out there
doing its job and
i answer a lot of questions on stack
overflow for instance and i see a lot of
people coming in with
stuff about bioinformatics lately i'm
not sure why that is
this summer there's a lot of stuff
people just trying to do small jobs
where they don't want to learn
too much about a particular community
because
what they're doing with their
programming is just a very small part of
their job
i use it uh a lot with my customers who
are doing data exchange between
different services
business to business things where you
know they get in a bunch of data from
some service and they need to pull out
the parts that matter to them and then
they
repackage that and send it on to some
other service yeah it's very
very strong with for being the glue of
things and sort of the text
transformation
side of things isn't it yeah absolutely
and we have some
and cpan which we call the killer
feature of pearl the comprehensive pearl
archive network
has tons and tons of packages for doing
quite a
bit of the stuff that people want to do
so if we take that away
then we're sort of really stuck so many
people have been doing pearl for so long
that someone has probably done the tasks
that you were trying to do
and put that thing on cpan this archive
network so that you can reuse the
results of
whatever they're doing and you know this
isn't unique to perl
python ruby node all these communities
have this sort of thing
curiously this idea came not from the
pearl community but
from the tech community you know the the
layout engine
from donald knuth they had the ctan the
comprehensive tech archive network
where if you're type setting your
document and you need some sort of
special feature there's probably a
package on there that does it
pearl sort of copied that and i think r
has done that now too there's a
conference of our
archive network it makes sense that the
tech people and the
the r people would know about each other
since they're probably both in the same
space
well thanks for mentioning cpan because
that was one of my
questions around the ecosystem which is
now met to cpan hasn't it
not changed this year was it well so
there's cpan which is just
this collection of sites that are synced
the same directories
and then there's these front ends to
them so there's this thing called
metacpan.org and this is a website which
is sort of a user interface into these
servers that are basically just big
directories of packages
there's some sort of index files that
let you know where to find things
a long time ago i think this same year
that that we started talking about pearl
six gram bar
showcased this site called
search.cpan.org
the cpan had gotten so big that you
couldn't just go look at the list
anymore
and discover things that you wanted so
he had this little search engine for it
and just a couple years ago all of that
transferred to now be this new version
of that called meta cpan
i i still have a fondness for the old
search.cpan.org but
there's a lot a lot of features in meta
cpan that make it very easy to get to
what you want
yeah me too i like the i remember
stealing some of the css from it
years ago and it's just so fast i'd like
to move us along from the
intersection we're just closing off with
the question of
what's the best way for someone new to
pearl to to learn it
well that's that's a bit loaded because
you're asking the person who wrote a
book called learning pearl
that's fine so so there's
a lot of ways that people can learn
pearl there are some online tutorials
there's my book the only book learning
pearl well now there's there's some
other books out there i want to be fair
there's another one that i think is good
from
curtis poe called beginning pearl i
forget when it was published
it's probably a little bit older than
the last edition of my learning pearl oh
he's got one
modern pearl as well isn't he well so
chrome there's this guy chromatic who
wrote
modern pearl oh yeah that's right so
modern pearl is a
is a bit of a weird book so let me come
back to that in
just a moment so you could read learning
pearl
you could go with beginning pearl i mean
curtis's book is
is very good there are some online
tutorials and all of this
i have noticed this thing this summer
that people have been writing to me
saying that they're learning pearl from
a book that we finished you know more
than 15 years ago when there's several
editions after this
the thing that i would encourage people
to do is find the most up-to-date
sources you can get and
not just in pearl but in any language i
mean i just spent a week
trying to figure out uh hugo this this
templating engine thing written in go
and i had to use a particular version
but so reading older docs didn't help me
reading
newer docs didn't help me that's one of
the things you think about but
besides that get the book try things out
just
try to program you're going to learn a
lot of stuff just by the act of actually
trying to run programs you're going to
learn
some about programming just the
mechanics of it but also doing the pearl
exercises
you'll learn those too there's a website
called
the pearl weekly challenge i think
that's it run by
muhammad anwar he puts up i think
i've got this right he puts up a
different problem every week
and different people solve it and then
explain how they solved it and so it's
also very good to look at people's
examples
yeah i'll make sure i get that in the in
the show notes let me say one thing
about modern pearl though so chromatic
has written this book and as its name
suggests
it's it's sort of an update to how you
should do perl
a lot of people recommend that as a
beginner book but it's
it's a very slim book and if you read
through it it's it's good if you
already know the language or you have
some experience programming
because he he quickly passes over some
targets
or some some topics that as programmers
we don't really think that much about
but i i just know from teaching classes
and be in front of people
that things that we take for granted
really trip people up until they they
grasp it
i mean like the whole idea of a
subroutine if you're not a programmer
and you haven't thought about this sort
of thing before
that's that's a huge concept once you
get it it's very simple
but that's really the way that learning
pearl is thinking about things it's like
we
we need to spell a lot of things out
because we just don't know where you are
yeah i learned pearl it was 2004 with
learning pearl third edition
which unfortunately isn't your one but
it was a very
sort of nice stepping stone with each
chapter building on the next
right i want to move us forward to the
bulk of the show which is now pearl 7.
the next section we've kind of crossed
over this one so that's great
so let's just get straight into the meat
of the show which is pearl seven
and he did a nice intro on pearl six for
us um which is fantastic
so it was said in the pearl seven
announcement
which i think you wrote that pearl seven
is going to be
pearl 5.32 but with different
cena more modern defaults have i got
that right
yeah i think i put the adjectives in
that order it sounds right
excellent so what are these new modern
defaults
and what were they okay so we've already
talked a little bit about pearl six
and just to sort of set some context for
how
they want to do this in pearl seven
pearl six took about 15 years to get
something
in people's hands that they could
actually use i we mentioned
and started around 2000 where we had the
idea but i would say that the real pearl
6 effort started around
2006 when audrey tang made this thing
called pugs
which was a haskell-based interpreter
for pearl 6. and now people could
actually start
playing with code and then it's not
until
10 years later or so that they actually
have a release
that's an extraordinary long time to
wait for this sort of thing
and it was because that thing i talked
about earlier where everything was open
to change
so we've we've had this pain this
particular pain where we can break
anything
and we saw what happened and we saw how
long it took to get something so now
let's talk about what you said about my
announcement with pearl 7.
pearl 532 pearl major version 5
with minor version 32 is out now
it was just released a couple months ago
in june i think
so we want to make this major version
jump
and there's a few reasons that anyone
wants to make a major version jump first
is you you could say we can do new
things in this major version we don't
have to necessarily support everything
in the previous
major version okay we've had this desire
since 2000
when we wanted to do pearl 6. we just
haven't been able to figure it out yet
so now we want to do this we're at pearl
five
pearl six was this thing that eventually
became raku and
went on to live uh on its own and at
this point pro 5 is
was born in 94 so it's what 20
yeah yeah six years it's old
yeah yeah and we've learned quite a bit
from there so anyway so
next major version will be seven but
what we don't want to do is wait 15
years to put this thing out
and so we can go in the opposite
direction and say what we're going to do
is take what we have now
we're just going to change the version
number so we're not writing new code
we're not rearranging
a bunch of stuff we're not inventing new
stuff we're not going to
go crazy but we're going to take this
small step to put a new major version on
this thing and see what that
forces us to do now once we do that
there are a bunch of things in pearl 5
which we
mostly do now or some people do now i
should say
but you have to turn on like
there is a a feature called strict which
i think javascript has now i heard and
maybe python
that's right where i want to use this
variable i have to tell you i want to
use this variable before i can use it
that way
if you misspell it later or use the
wrong variable name or something it it
yells at you but you have to turn that
on so
would be really nice if we could that
would just start being turned on
because we tell everyone to use it all
the time we tell everyone you should
always use it
you're not using this come back when
you've used it that sort of thing well
let's just make it the default
but if we do that now for pearl 5 and
people are still trying to run their
pearl 5 programs all of a sudden they
break
there are some other things that would
be very nice to get the problem is if i
start listing all these then people are
going to think that the pearl 7
developers are actually committing to
these and and we actually don't know
what is going to be on by default and
off by default just yet because we're
still
talking about well let's just say pearl
7 is
coming but the big caveat it could all
change
yes that's gonna ruin all my questions
so we're just gonna pretend
that these things are kind of there so
so some of the things that we could turn
on by default
there's this experimental feature in
pearl five now called signatures
so if you're writing in many other
languages you know that you can
give it the subroutine name and then
some sort of signature
that describes the parameters it can
take and then there can be some various
checks based on those
and pearl we have that feature it's
experimental so it's not on
by default but it'd be wonderful if it
was now
it might not be on by default in perl
seven but
now we have a chance to sort of mutate
the language in a way
that we can get the stuff that
everyone's trying to use anyway without
disturbing
all of the backward compatibility that
we've been committed to in pearl5
we put that in a new major version and
it makes that a little bit easier
again we're not changing the code we're
not adding new features because the
feature is already there we just turn
them on
now that everyone gets them for free and
if your stuff conflicts with what
these defaults are then uh you still
have pearl 5 available
i please don't anyone upgrade anything
until you've tested it not just perl but
any
sort of language or or new version of
something so what's going to happen with
pearl 5 since you just mentioned pro 5
is still
so the the commitment that the pearl 5
porters have made and these are the
people who maintain the actual pearl
interpreter
is that instead of the normal two-year
support policy we have now for any
point release of pearl like 5 32 or 5
30.
they are going to extend the maintenance
period for 532 as it is now
to be very very long and we're talking
15 years something in that range
so we're going to keep supporting
whatever the the last
version of pearl 5 is so people can stay
in that and have some stability
you don't have to adopt pearl this year
then all of a sudden next year
it's a whole new thing we're gonna have
that available
part of this puzzle and and this is out
of the control of
the people developing pearl is that the
operating systems distribute what they
want
we talked a little bit about the mac
earlier
that's why i was just going to ask yeah
they hold a lot of power don't they
so if you have umbutu for instance and
pearl 7 exists when you run pearl
on your ubuntu machine which one do you
get
well i hope that the distributions are
very smart and they keep the pearl five
one for a while
it's supported it's uh people are taking
care of it
uh it's a thing that everyone expects
right now
and i also hope and and this is just a
hope my
personal opinion is that maybe there'll
be this thing called
pearl seven so there's a binary on your
computer that is just pearl
and that's pearl five like people expect
and then there's this other one
pearl seven and you can play fancy games
with the links and stuff like that if
you like
and then after a while a fewer people
would be using just a straight pearl
five one people will catch up or make
their decisions about that and
the distributions can see what their
particular users want
yeah i think that's what um python did
for quite a while isn't it
yes 2.7 and then three point x
and then you default for a user bin
python or
user bin parallel to a sim link to
whatever you want
yeah so on my mac i have both of those
pythons if i just say python i get
python 2.7 because that's what most
people expect
and but if i want python 3 i just type
out python 3
and i get that some people have not been
happy with that python transition
but also i mean looking at the bright
side of the world hasn't ended python
has gone on
python is still gaining in popularity
it's
sometimes things are just hardened and
maybe a little bit uncomfortable but
life goes on yeah i experienced exactly
that
distro forcing upgrade that we were just
discussing
with um ansible in a oh geez
continuous integration continuous
deployment gitlab thing
i think it was um arc linux
whatever the distro is that docker uses
default
that switched to python 3 and broke
everything so well this so this is an
interesting case because i've been using
arch linux
online just because a friend suggested
it and i'll say i've never used
this before so i'll try it out and there
they are always trying to be on the
latest of
everything and they seem to do a pretty
good job of it so
that's different than say like a red hat
enterprise edition where they're like
stability stability stability you get
the same thing you know exactly what you
get
we're not going to change things out
from under you versus this cutting edge
if it's new it's there the next day or
even sooner
um how's that gonna work out and
i think this i mean i we don't need to
do a whole podcast on this bit but there
is
you know this whole class of people now
devops and these upgraded sysadmin
types who really think about this sort
of stuff to provide a consistent
experience
despite the fact of all the stuff that's
changing everywhere in the world
every day not just perl not just node
not just
your operating system but all sorts of
things get
get changed and your stuff has to
somehow keep working
so hopefully i think the pearl
developers are are taking care of this
they're talking to the people they need
to talk to
in the various package managers that we
can
come up with a way to give something
people they expect at the same time
giving them a taste of what they can get
in the future yeah i think there's a lot
of
existing case studies to draw experience
on
when they do get to that calling all
developers
there's no telling what you can create
when you upgrade your data platform to
inner systems iris
are you ready to build the applications
you want however you want them
are you ready to develop applications
faster than ever collaborate
build faster and deploy more efficiently
tomorrow's next breakthroughs are
waiting for you today
intersystems iris data platform ready
set code start coding for free
visit intersystems.com try to try iris
so you've mentioned um strict which is
the generally a mantra that you should
always
use in a good way and there's another
is pragma the correct word here yeah
so that would be like using a module
isn't it
so how would you describe that to people
that aren't familiar with
so there's there's the technical answer
and then there's sort of the social
answer with this a pragma
is something like a setting so
strict you say in a pro program use
strict
i want to turn this feature called
strict on
or use warnings or use utf-8 or whatever
it is
i am telling the compiler to enable
these features
now technically these features are
enabled as modules
behind the scene and a module is just a
packaged little bit of code
that sits on its own so in other
languages you might
say import or include or yeah something
like that
so usually when you see a pro crab
file whatever form it's in you would
look to see
use strict and use warnings or
another module that has a ton of
defaults switched on
like a wrapper like modern pearl or
something
so you've already mentioned how strict
might change
what would happen with warnings as well
i think
one of the options that they're looking
at is having them on by default
so i would be fine with that there and
there are
you mentioned some of these wrappers
like modern pearl or mojo base or
something like this that enable a bunch
of stuff
for you so you have instead of you know
10 lines of boilerplate you have
this one thing that does it for you
that's fine
warnings i have a particular and
unpopular opinion about
that this is a development tool and if
you aren't developing
then and no one's looking at the
warnings or doing anything with the
warnings then
they're a waste of time having the
warnings in there is not a waste of time
using it as a development tool is not a
waste of time but
if you're sitting there in a production
environment and no one's monitoring the
logs
and you have a program that is spitting
out you know one warning every second
you're filling up your disk you're
you're making your logs more noisy
if you have someone that's looking at
that and fixing that stuff so those
warnings disappear
that's great but i find in a lot of
places people have
quite a bit to do already in their jobs
and those sort of things go by the
wayside
so having it on by default would not
make me personally happy
but i think it would probably make the
world a little bit better
and if you want to just turn it off in
production that's
very easy to do so the plan really is to
turn on what everyone would normally
turn on manually but allow them to
switch off
if it's a problem yes and that's one of
the big things to think about
when we're looking at this scary thing
called bumping your major version
we're trying to make pearl seven the
same as pearl 532 and we're just going
to switch
on or switch off different things
so all you have to do to get back to the
old behavior is
flip the various bits on those things to
their original settings
which makes it very easy for us to make
some sort of pearl 5 compatibility mode
how this is going to work i don't know
yet they're talking about the particular
syntax and people's preferences and
stuff like that
so since pearl 7 and pearl 532 should be
pretty much close to the same thing and
there's just a difference in how they
set things if pearl 7 the new thing is
reading a program and it
somehow thinks that it's pearl 5 written
for pearl five it can just
say hey i'm going to go back to the 532
settings and you should be fine
we don't know if that's going to require
something in your pearl 5 program or a
setting in your pearl 7 program yet
but that's certainly the intent at the
same time
if you're writing a new pearl 7 stuff i
think what they want people to do now is
declare
in this new code this way that would
really help us out is
say use version 7.
now when your pro 5 program tries to run
that or your pro 5 interpreter tries to
run that
it sees that thing and says oh you're
asking for seven but i'm only five
and it can lead you very quickly to what
you need to do with that use a different
interpreter or or something like that
one of the things that a lot of people
are very concerned about is how cpan
which is all code written for pearl 5 is
going to interact with this new thing
called pearl 7.
well if we get this compatibility mode
right and i don't think there's a chance
that we'll
we'll get it wrong but if we get this
thing right
pearl 7 the interpreter can read through
the stuff say oh you're loading a module
from pearl 5 i will
make the settings be whatever pearl 5
settings are and then this stuff should
be just fine
it justifiably i think makes a lot of
people really nervous
because there are a couple hundred
thousand packages on cpn
yeah but they're not just dumped there
there's a whole ecosystem of
smoke tests and testers and automation
that
you could run on a copy of the whole
thing or a portion of it and this is a
massive relief
that you can toggle something whether
it's one way or the other
to get back to where you were for a
certain period you know
so this is an amazing thing about the
pearl community and especially when they
got into the testing
mindset and i think michael schwern was
a big part of this
that there are people who test all of
cpan against any new
release of pearl 5. so we're talking
like i said couple hundred thousand
modules
so they just have these machines in the
background going through testing
everything
a new little bit of syntax comes out and
my module from that i wrote 15 years ago
breaks on this new little piece of
syntax i get an email from someone
saying hey
i tested your module on this new release
of pearl and there's this problem
now there's no obligation for me to go
fix that i mean it's open source i could
you know just sort of be anti-social and
let it sit but
usually the fix is very simple it's i
just need to adjust how i use some call
or something like that
and i can release a new thing and and
now my module works for
the the new version too and like you
said we have this this stuff in place in
pearl
that we can find out where the problems
are very quickly
you mentioned cpan smokers this is a
collection of machines
that download or check out whatever the
current branch of
of perl is whatever pearl's doing
before we've released that version and
test it on all sorts of different
operating systems
and these are just volunteers doing this
so we quickly get feedback from a lot of
different places that you know we made
this small code change and add this
feature does it work
now beyond that there's a thing called
cpan testers
so i upload a module a third-party bit
of code
onto cpan the comprehensive perl archive
network
and immediately all sorts of machines
all from volunteers start downloading
this testing and sending their results
back
not i mean it's it's brilliant that we
have this but
you know i just uploaded a module
yesterday an update and
now i'm getting all this feedback about
all these places i have failed and i
have to go debug
yeah you asked for it though didn't you
it's a nice problem to have though
it's a great thing about the community
but there was wasn't there something
last week
this is a bit of a diversion but there
was something that
had some type of observation in it oh it
was
the fake iphone rooting kit or something
that had been on cpan for years but it
was so obscure
i think you're talking about module auto
load
and i i had never used it or something
that came out
and and on and we don't know if anyone
ever used it
so everyone who is program pearl has
probably experienced this at some point
you try to run a program and it stops
and it says can't locate
blah blah blah in at inc and it gives
you this big mess of
of stuff pearl is looking for some
module
and it didn't find it and it just
complained and
the error message is very much geared
towards programmers
which is not the nicest way to present
information to casual programmers
so there's this thing called module auto
use
which i think the intent originally was
if it ran into a
a module you tried to use and it
couldn't find it
it would do various things to make that
work out and again i
haven't looked at the code so i don't
really know what it was doing
but yeah like you said apparently it had
some sort of malicious
thing there where when you when it ran
this module
would phone home to somewhere and then
download something and
usually we have found that stuff pretty
quickly because
someone notices it notifies
the the cpan administrators there's this
group called pause the pearl authors
upload server
and those people are paying attention
every day
and they quickly remove stuff like that
um we've had this problem
a handful of times in you know the past
20 years yeah it's pretty rare and it's
not like it
this stuff's auto installed anywhere you
have to explicitly go and get it
so so how that one lived so long i don't
know if it was like
taken over somehow and then slightly
updated when no one was looking
or you know it's doing one of those
things where in the test environment
it it doesn't do the bad thing yeah my
point of mentioning that
other than an interesting story is that
there's a whole
different cascade of teams and groups
that work on the this
public code that everyone contributes to
and it gets found it's not just a big
part of
stuff that people upload things to and
i'm surprised that that this situation
has gone on for so long
i'm just this group of volunteers um
mostly led by um this guy in germany
andreas koenig
these guys started in 93 or 94 calling
themselves the pearl pack rats
and then they just started collecting
stuff and then they made this thing that
takes in the modules and puts them all
somewhere and then like we mentioned
meta-cpan now there's a search engine on
top of that and
it's it's almost completely
run by volunteers with no funding i'm
not
sure if there's something similar in
other ecosystems but
the other ecosystems i've seen sort of
rely on github where
you it'll go look on github for
something
and just whatever the latest release or
master branches or
tag or something like that is a little
harder to curate that
because you don't control what's
actually in the repository it could be
anything
i know other communities have had i'm
not going to call anyone out but they've
had their sort of embarrassing moments
with
that sort of stuff and we shouldn't be
so snide about that because it happened
to us too just now
yeah no we shouldn't point on that for
anyone right i'm going to do some quick
fire questions
okay for some fun so here we go
what are bare word file handles and how
will they change
okay so when pearl first started it was
very quick and dirty language there's
a way that we access a file either to
read to it or write to it
and that is all controlled through this
thing called a file handle
a bare word file handle is one of these
nice perl variables that doesn't have
the funny character out front the thing
we call a sigil
so you'd say open and it's usually in
all uppercase like
file or fh is my favorite or you know
whatever you want
the problem that pearl has is figuring
out what that thing is because it's
going along
and it doesn't have the funny character
out front so that was completely fine
and the way we did things before pearl
5.6 when we introduced the ability to
put these
file handles inside variables normal
variables that have a funny dollar sign
out front
uh so if we can get rid of those a lot
of things can get simplified
i guess another good way to say this is
if you've seen
the like word standard out standard
error or standard in
in a program in parallel be all
uppercase those are bare word file
handles
and those will stick around yes like a
macro
and see parlance um i don't know if i'd
go that far but yeah
we'll say that an uppercase word as well
yes oh yeah yeah yeah it's an uppercase
word
okay right full stop on that one okay
next one what are subroutine signatures
and how will they
change okay so so right now perl
subroutines did we answer the
last one actually are they going to
change bare word 500 you're trying to
get rid of them that's the they we want
to turn them off so that you can't use
them
but you can also the the system once
will stick around
okay signatures i think we touched on
this pre earlier didn't we a little bit
yeah so the way the pro works now and
it's sort of quick and dirty to get
things done
attitude is that when you pass
parameters to a
subroutine it just makes a big list of
everything together and gives it to the
subroutine and the subroutine looks in
this big list
and then has to pick apart what belongs
to what based on whatever you're doing
signatures most people who are
programming it not perl will probably
recognize these
make a formal parameter list to the
subroutine it says the first thing is
this
the second thing is this the third
through fifth things are these
and so you don't have to do that inside
the code at the last moment
perl has the ability to do that we want
we would love to turn them on by default
i think it's unlikely that we'll get
that right away
for various reasons but also
the old way will still be available you
can still do it exactly as you did
before
but at least with pearl 7 you can use
that as a
you know a line in the sand to say
here's all the new stuff and i'll give
some
people somewhere to go and look and see
that all these things are available
and i think one of the only thing that's
really holding signatures up is that
they want to add a few more
niceties to it before they they say this
is the feature and we're gonna
make it on by default okay full stop on
that one
what are prototypes and how will they
change okay so
prototypes are related to the signatures
and the
the argument passing so perl being the
sort of
language that it is this dynamic
language it doesn't exactly know what
it's doing
next because all sorts of things could
have changed out from under it as it's
parsing through
the code prototypes were a way to tell
a subroutine what sort of things it
should expect after
you call it like you have uh you know
two arguments or you have
an array or you have whatever the syntax
the place that you you put this
prototype in a subroutine to tell it how
to
extract pearl to parse is in the same
place we want to put signatures
and it looks very close to the signature
syntax
so what we need to do is either put this
attribute in front of this thing
and say colon prototype so we know that
this thing is a prototype and not a
signature
or not use prototypes which is probably
the
better answer so there is this little
tug of war between
right now between prototypes which is
this old thing
that i think larry wall always sort of
envisioned turning into
signatures but did not and signatures
and this is why signatures may not
get the nod for the first go of pearl
seven
we have to figure out that tug of war
and how much of cpan and user's code
we're gonna break
by making signatures the priority rather
than prototypes
so one of those two could win or they
could be merged or so
we're definitely trying to get rid of
prototypes but
but yeah okay how much breakage do we
want to want to take on the first go
we've mentioned larry wall a few times
where does he sit in
the whole pearl ecosystem at the moment
right now i sort of envision him sitting
at home enjoying his life
and watching his creations go out and do
wonderful things in the universe
in 2000 we had this split where pearl
six started and was going to do its
thing and larry wall really
paid attention to that now unbeknownst
to us at the time
and we were on pearl 5.8 then that
invigorated a section of the pearl
community
and we ended up with pearl 510 at the
same time this pearl 6 development was
going on
i think yorako high and tanime was
mostly responsible for that
and then pearl 5 just kept going but
larry was paying attention to pearl 6.
designing this
100-year language is what he called it
yes if larry's on board then
everyone pays attention like if linus
devold did something in linux
yes same sort of power yeah and so i
think
when and we we had this this move of
governance in pearl 5 to go from
larry wall who is the final answer on
everything
to respected individuals taking over we
had jesse vincent
who sort of rejiggered the entire
development process for this new reality
and
that was an amazing step forward ricardo
cygnus took it even further and now
there's this guy sawyer x who's in
charge of that he's the pumpkin
what they call they call the pumpkin
which is this funny phrase that
they took from chip salsenberg i believe
where they had to share some
piece of hardware it was a printer or a
tape reader or something
you could only use it if you physically
possessed this little pumpkin plush toy
that way your computer didn't stop
whatever my computer was doing but
the idea there is that we sort of have
this
more committee geared
development model i don't really like
saying it like that but it's it's no
longer larry is always right
if he came back i'm sure he he would be
right but i think he's he's enjoying his
retirement and
quite proud of the the two languages he
has out there now
along with the fact that he wrote the
patch command which for which i think he
got the um
he got some big award from some open
source foundation for
that's right and just for the listeners
all the names that brian's mentioning
i know because i'm in this sort of world
but they're all big famous names which
would be similar in
other languages key people in the
community well thanks for answering that
a couple of quick fire off ones again
okay what are indirect objects and how
will they change
so the the c plus plus programmers will
enjoy this one
we're actually trying to kill off
indirect objects just because it makes
the parsing situation
weird pearl has a lot of little
weirdities that make it
difficult to parse and i think it was
randall schwartz who said
only pearl can parse pearl yeah that's
another famous one
but so if you make a new object i this
might be true in java but i haven't
touched java in a long time
you would say you know variable equals
new dog for instance so there's a dog
class and you're making a new one so the
method is before
the class name and then after that you
get your your object or your instance
whatever you want to call in your
variable and you say that
dot whatever the method name is so when
you make the thing
you have the method out front but when
you use it you have the method the end
in perl that indirect object notation is
when you have that object
that that method name in front of the
object and you can do that in perl for
any
object it doesn't have to be just the
constructor the new thing
we have discouraged this for years and
years and years lots of the
documentation has caught up not to use
it
and if we can turn it off that would
allow
and not only turn it off but get people
to stop using it that would allow
the developers i think to forget about
that whole class of problems
in determining if we have a method call
going on
so it's kind of a heads up to say if
you're using that we're hoping to get
rid of it
yeah i think i don't think many people
are because i there's almost no place
that anyone sees it anymore except
maybe in some old old old module
documentation
okay so what is multi-dimensional array
emulation i like the sound of that so i
thought i'd ask
and is this new this this this one's
actually kind of funny i um when sawyer
told me he was going to
target this as something to turn off i
had actually forgotten what this was
this is a pearl 4 thing so pearl 4
came out in the early 90s sometime and
if we had
hashes and arrays and that's it and
these arrays
you it's flat the hashes are flat it's
the rays are just
this would be mobs yes in fact
if they weren't even called hashes then
they were called associative arrays
but they're like maps or dictionaries or
something like that
so you couldn't do multi-dimensional
structures like say you want to have
a matrix where you have rows and columns
well that just doesn't work
pearl 4 had no way to do that so what
they would do is they would make a hash
key
where they concatenate all the
dimensions the indexes of
all the dimensions with a semicolon and
that would be the hash keys
and then there would just be a single
value for that so it looks like you have
a matrix or a you know a 3d matrix or
something but you really just have this
hash
with all these funny looking keys now
the multi-dimensional bit is is if you
gave
the hash or you gave to the hash a a
list for its keys
instead of just a single string it would
take this list concatenate it in this
fancy way with the semicolons and then
go look for that instead of
doing something else this was a very
clever trick for people to get around
the fact that pearl had these sort of
well we call now primitive data
structures to do this multi-dimensional
circuit because it was a step in stone
before
you could do it properly yeah and and
the c people might even be more familiar
with this because you know you have to
do all that pointer
thing like where's the next row okay
jump ahead like
eight sizeofs whatever
i don't think i've ever seen anyone use
it for real
i completely forgot that it even existed
as a feature
but it's there it's there for the old
pro 4 days
there's another question that i want to
quickly slip in
we haven't mentioned we mentioned
objects and methods then but
what's the object-oriented world going
to be like in pearl
7 or you know how do people want it to
be is it going to be the separate
moo moose if people are familiar with
that separate
ecosystem within an ecosystem or is it
going to be
because you can do objects oriented with
pearl 5 since forever
but they've put all this extra easier
stuff on
so so this is an an interesting question
can you give me a proper answer
and i'll yeah i'll i will try um so you
you said two things you said um what is
it gonna be and what do people want
that is the tension in all of this stuff
there's what people say they want
and then there's like what they're
actually going to use because
and one of the things that has held up
these different object systems in pearl
that you've mentioned there's a thing
called moose
and then there's a variant of that
called mu in a variant called mouse and
a variant called mu
mu and so on and they're all different
different people's takes on how it
should be done yeah and and but the
thing is they're all sort of clustered
around some ideas
now there's a guy curtis poe the same
guy who i
i mentioned before has gone back and
looked at this and he has this
proposal called core c-o-r
that he has looked at all these things
and said
they're internally and cons they're all
internally inconsistent in some way
they're all trying to do something but
they didn't think about this or they
didn't think about that
and he's trying to pull all that into
this thing
which the pearl seven people the guys
who are actually
responsible for putting this stuff into
the code
have not told him no one now that's a
lot different than saying yes
so i don't want to get people's hopes up
that's why i say it that way
but they're definitely open to it
there's still a lot of discussion going
on with that
a lot of the stuff he's done has really
cleaned up a lot of the ideas that i
think other people were going toward
and we'll see what happens with that
we're not going to get it right away
this this jump from pearl 532 to pearl
7 should be quick no new features
to see that we can do it to figure out
what we need to do to actually make a
big jump
and then we can think about the other
stuff my take on all this sort of stuff
is that
i just tend to be a lot simpler in my
application of object-oriented
programming it's it's a set of
philosophies
not necessarily a set of syntax but
that's all i'll say about that
yeah i think there's a comparison
analogy whatever you can
make when you look at javascript world
and you've got things like react angular
vue.js if you're familiar with all that
and then they've all got their
different state managers on top and
depending on what you're doing and what
you like you can reach
for those different projects which is
how i see all the different
object-orientated stuff for perl you
have your core
javascript and your core pearl five but
you can build on loads of different
stuff depending on
what you like the look of is that right
or wrong and that
i think that's fair i i think often
people
choose the one they most agree with and
then just sort of force it into whatever
situation they have
probably much like the javascript
frameworks where you know you read
resumes or something they say i'm an
angular developer
well you know learn some other stuff too
it's
you put the proper role in the proper
job yeah learn
learn different languages because you
can steal stuff from all of them
so a lot of my questions in this last
session we've covered off i wanted to
ask you about compatible
compatibility mode but we've touched
that to appease anyone that's nervous
about the change you can always
switch stuff on or off that's the plan
cpan is gonna not break that's the
bottom line
well that's yeah that's definitely our
hope we have plenty of time to figure it
out
so my final question there was should we
be worried about all of our revenue
generating code
which other other people call legacy but
it's where the money gets made
so this is an interesting thing and i
like that you phrase it like that the
the money-making code
because what i sort of tell people when
i go to consult
is that if this is the stuff that's
making your money you don't want anyone
else to be able to change it
which means you don't want your
operating system to upgrade something
out from underneath you you don't want
your language to change module versions
on you you don't want
anything to change that you didn't
decide to change because
like you said that's your your money and
i i had one client that their website
was down
for a day and they estimated something
like they're losing three million
dollars an hour
so these things are important and if
they're important enough to make you
money they're important enough for you
to control
despite what pearl does lock that stuff
down
i know a lot of people that use things
like artifactory or something else to
make their own package repositories and
that's the only thing they can pull from
they know exactly which versions of
everything they're using what was that
called
dark pan dark pan that that's the phrase
we use for
all the pearl coat out there that we
never see
and we don't know what people are doing
or how they're doing it
okay and trying to support that is
really interesting and
i know we're getting close to the end of
the interview so i don't want to go into
all that stuff but it's really fun to
talk about
maintaining cpan and if you want to
really interview someone interesting on
that neil bowers is doing some amazing
work yeah i've tried to nail before
i don't want to make this too clicky
with everyone but
um like i was saying before this year
it's this is one of the you've been one
of the guys i've been looking forward to
interviewing
every name you've mentioned is i i know
in those types of circles
yeah that says i don't really do
anything fun or interesting or clever i
just
write about what other people do oh it's
it's all fun
i think we've covered all the things
that are out there at the moment and
what's kind of
kind of happened to them bottom line
being correct me if i'm wrong we don't
need to worry too much
if you're a user in perl are there any
things
sort of in perl seven that you want
people to be really excited about
or you know you envision at 2000.com
revert you know phoenix from the fire
that's going to attract loads of stuff
or you know
what do you feel about all that there
are some things
that i could be excited about that i
haven't had the chance to be excited
about just because i never thought
pearl 5 would take this big jump pearl 7
i'm not
i'm very cautiously optimistic because
it's it's going to be this transition
step
where we know that we have updated the
code that we can change the major
version we know that we can do these
things
and then the i think the feeling now is
purl eight is we're gonna
see significant change we know that we
can do it in pearl seven we've got all
our processes in place we figured out
how to do it and now
we can just do it again with pearl 8 and
now we can really break things
i'm i would really love to see
signatures but again might not happen
for pearl 7.
so and one of the things that i'd like
to leave with is i do have this book
through pearl school on lean pub called
preparing for pearl seven which is
really
yeah i've got that in the in the show
notes and i'll give it myself as well
it's really what you need to be doing
today or what practices you need you
could be doing in pearl five now that
can help you so that you
have a seamless transition the
interesting thing about this book is
each sort of feature that we've talked
about has its own chapter and i've i've
put a status
at the beginning of it probable unlikely
you know something like that
and that's that's sort of changing as it
as it goes some things are they're
thinking oh we
we thought about that at first but now
it looks like it might be a tough sell
and other things that we hadn't thought
about are look like they might be likely
the great thing about pearl school and
in lean pubs all these things
are epubs so when i find out new stuff i
can just push a new version
you know i could do maybe three shows
about pearl there's
whole projects like the more delicious
web framework
there's your pearl power tools so we'll
have some notes and
those are really tom christensen's poor
pearl power tools i just
maintain the color yeah you're looking
after them
i've got a ton of other stuff but yeah
we've kind of run out of time
so obviously pearl has a bright future
and you're very much part of that um but
if there's one thing a software engineer
should remember from our show what would
you like that to be
oh geez from today's show and all the
things we talked about yeah
i would go to the top i think that
besides the fact that pearl 7 is coming
in i think it's going to be really nice
is that no matter what you're doing what
field you're in
what tools you're using is is control
your tools
be up to date on what they're doing stay
up to date on them
because things are going to change in
the future no matter what you're doing
okay and was there anything we've got a
few minutes left
was there anything we missed that you'd
like to mention
being silly enough to miss you know i
don't know i
i think i think you've covered a lot of
it uh if people want to know more about
pearl
uh they can start at www.pearl.org
that's the
the main site the meta cpan.org is a
great place to find modules
and pearl5 recently transferred to
github from a a private git repo that it
was using
um which it had been on after being on
perforce for a long time
so you can actually go and look at this
stuff go to github
at the uh i keep forgetting what the
organization name is and what the
repo name is i get them backed up one's
pearl and one's probably that's what
google's for so doesn't matter
yeah and and there's stuff on the wiki
todd ronaldo who's been leading a lot of
the modernization efforts has been
keeping really good notes
in the wiki so you can see what people
are talking about
how things are going and participate
whatever your comfort level is
is that the best place to keep up to
date with pearl 7
or where should you subscribe to or um
that stick around
i i don't have any good answers for that
other than my preparing for pearl 7 book
because there's there's this nice
trade-off you can either pay attention
minutely every day
which i don't particularly like to do or
you you check in every so often but you
miss a lot of stuff and i
i try to in all of my writing including
my effective pro programming blog i try
to fill in that gap where you don't have
to pay attention but you're going to get
the stuff you need to know but i'll do a
show on pearlite and then we can cover
off all of that
i'll just hold my hands off okay a few
of these questions weren't nicked from
your book
um that's because it's really good
quality um but we didn't have that much
time to go too deep
so people can follow you on twitter um
but how else do you like
people to get in touch or do you like
people getting in touch
i i do stuff on twitter i don't often
carry out conversations there
they can dm me if they like but my email
is easy to find i put it everywhere
so people can email me directly if they
like
i'm on stack overflow on reddit and all
these places
if you're reading about perl you've
probably run across me there
i tend to take communication any way
that people
want to do it just because trying to
make people
do it the way i like tends not to work
out just let them do whatever they're
comfortable with and i'll try to adapt
to it
excellent answer thanks um brian thank
you for coming on the show
yes thank you it's been a real pleasure
and this is gavin henry for software
engineering radio thank you for
listening
developers take your marks it's time to
upgrade your data
platform to inner systems iris it's time
to deliver complex mission critical
applications in the fastest route
possible
it's time to use any data from any
source it's time to embed analytics and
create interactive user interfaces
so what are you waiting for choose your
language choose your tools
choose your environment collaborate
build faster and deploy more efficiently
done and done tomorrow's next
breakthroughs are waiting for you today
intersystems iris data platform the
fastest way to build applications
ready set code
start coding for free visit
intersystems.com
try to try iris
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at se
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at
scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening